<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Linguolab</string>

    <string-array name="r00fairy">
        <item>The Princess and the Pea</item>
        <item>B</item>
        <item>C</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="r00Qfairy">
        <item>qr00q101</item>
        <item>qr00q102</item>
        <item>qr00q103</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr00q101">
        <item>8 May 1835</item>
        <item>Hans Christian Andersen</item>
        <item>A long time ago there were a king and queen who were unhappy because they were childless. But it happened that once when the queen was bathing, a frog crept out of the water on to the land, and said to her, "Your wish shall be fulfilled, before a year has gone by, you shall have a daughter."
            What the frog had said came true, and the queen had a little girl who was so pretty that the king could not contain himself for joy, and ordered a great feast. He invited not only his kindred, friends and acquaintances, but also the wise women, in order that they might be kind and well disposed towards the child. There were thirteen of them in his kingdom, but, as he had only twelve golden plates for them to eat out of, one of them had to be left at home.
The feast was held with all manner of splendor and when it came to an end the wise women bestowed their magic gifts upon the baby - one gave virtue, another beauty, a third riches, and so on with everything in the world that one can wish for.

When eleven of them had made their promises, suddenly the thirteenth came in. She wished to avenge herself for not having been invited, and without greeting, or even looking at anyone, she cried with a loud voice, "The king's daughter shall in her fifteenth year prick herself with a spindle, and fall down dead." And, without saying a word more, she turned round and left the room.

They were all shocked, but the twelfth, whose good wish still remained unspoken, came forward, and as she could not undo the evil sentence, but only soften it, she said, it shall not be death, but a deep sleep of a hundred years, into which the princess shall fall.

The king, who would fain keep his dear child from the misfortune, gave orders that every spindle in the whole kingdom should be burnt. Meanwhile the gifts of the wise women were plenteously fulfilled on the young girl, for she was so beautiful, modest, good-natured, and wise, that everyone who saw her was bound to love her.

It happened that on the very day when she was fifteen years old, the king and queen were not at home, and the maiden was left in the palace quite alone. So she went round into all sorts of places, looked into rooms and bed-chambers just as she liked, and at last came to an old tower. She climbed up the narrow winding staircase, and reached a little door. A rusty key was in the lock, and when she turned it the door sprang open, and there in a little room sat an old woman with a spindle, busily spinning her flax.

"Good day, old mother," said the king"s daughter, "what are you doing there?"

"I am spinning," said the old woman, and nodded her head.

"What sort of thing is that, that rattles round so merrily," said the girl, and she took the spindle and wanted to spin too. But scarcely had she touched the spindle when the magic decree was fulfilled, and she pricked her finger with it.

And, in the very moment when she felt the prick, she fell down upon the bed that stood there, and lay in a deep sleep. And this sleep extended over the whole palace, the king and queen who had just come home, and had entered the great hall, began to go to sleep, and the whole of the court with them. The horses, too, went to sleep in the stable, the dogs in the yard, the pigeons upon the roof, the flies on the wall, even the fire that was flaming on the hearth became quiet and slept, the roast meat left off frizzling, and the cook, who was just going to pull the hair of the scullery boy, because he had forgotten something, let him go, and went to sleep. And the wind fell, and on the trees before the castle not a leaf moved again.

But round about the castle there began to grow a hedge of thorns, which every year became higher, and at last grew close up round the castle and all over it, so that there was nothing of it to be seen, not even the flag upon the roof. But the story of the beautiful sleeping Briar Rose, for so the princess was named, went about the country, so that from time to time kings' sons came and tried to get through the thorny hedge into the castle. But they found it impossible, for the thorns held fast together, as if they had hands, and the youths were caught in them, could not get loose again, and died a miserable death.

After long, long years a king's son came again to that country, and heard an old man talking about the thorn hedge, and that a castle was said to stand behind it in which a wonderfully beautiful princess, named Briar Rose, had been asleep for a hundred years, and that the king and queen and the whole court were asleep likewise. He had heard, too, from his grandfather, that many kings, sons had already come, and had tried to get through the thorny hedge, but they had remained sticking fast in it, and had died a pitiful death.

Then the youth said, "I am not afraid, I will go and see the beautiful Briar Rose." The good old man might dissuade him as he would, he did not listen to his words.

But by this time the hundred years had just passed, and the day had come when Briar Rose was to awake again. When the king's son came near to the thorn hedge, it was nothing but large and beautiful flowers, which parted from each other of their own accord, and let him pass unhurt, then they closed again behind him like a hedge. In the castle yard he saw the horses and the spotted hounds lying asleep, on the roof sat the pigeons with their heads under their wings. And when he entered the house, the flies were asleep upon the wall, the cook in the kitchen was still holding out his hand to seize the boy, and the maid was sitting by the black hen which she was going to pluck.

He went on farther, and in the great hall he saw the whole of the court lying asleep, and up by the throne lay the king and queen. Then he went on still farther, and all was so quiet that a breath could be heard, and at last he came to the tower, and opened the door into the little room where Briar Rose was sleeping.

There she lay, so beautiful that he could not turn his eyes away, and he stooped down and gave her a kiss. But as soon as he kissed her, Briar Rose opened her eyes and awoke, and looked at him quite sweetly.

Then they went down together, and the king awoke, and the queen, and the whole court, and looked at each other in great astonishment. And the horses in the courtyard stood up and shook themselves, the hounds jumped up and wagged their tails, the pigeons upon the roof pulled out their heads from under their wings, looked round, and flew into the open country, the flies on the wall crept again, the fire in the kitchen burned up and flickered and cooked the meat, the joint began to turn and sizzle again, and the cook gave the boy such a box on the ear that he screamed, and the maid finished plucking the fowl.

And then the marriage of the king's son with Briar Rose was celebrated with all splendor, and they lived contented to the end of their days.
Wasn’t this a lady of real delicacy?


        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr00q102">
        <item>1979</item>
        <item>Franko22</item>
        <item>text12222</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr00q103">
        <item>2009</item>
        <item>Franko33</item>
        <item>text13333333</item>
    </string-array>


    <string-array name="r01fairy">
        <item>The Princess and the Pea</item>
        <item>B analis</item>
        <item>C analis</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="r01Qfairy">
        <item>qr01q101</item>
        <item>qr01q102</item>
        <item>qr01q103</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr01q101">
        <item>8 May 1835</item>
        <item>Hans Christian Andersen</item>
        <item>A long time ago there were a king and queen who were unhappy because they were childless. But it happened that once when the queen was bathing, a frog crept out of the water on to the land, and said to her, "Your wish shall be fulfilled, before a year has gone by, you shall have a daughter."
            What the frog had said came true, and the queen had a little girl who was so pretty that the king could not contain himself for joy, and ordered a great feast. He invited not only his kindred, friends and acquaintances, but also the wise women, in order that they might be kind and well disposed towards the child. There were thirteen of them in his kingdom, but, as he had only twelve golden plates for them to eat out of, one of them had to be left at home.
The feast was held with all manner of splendor and when it came to an end the wise women bestowed their magic gifts upon the baby - one gave virtue, another beauty, a third riches, and so on with everything in the world that one can wish for.

When eleven of them had made their promises, suddenly the thirteenth came in. She wished to avenge herself for not having been invited, and without greeting, or even looking at anyone, she cried with a loud voice, "The king's daughter shall in her fifteenth year prick herself with a spindle, and fall down dead." And, without saying a word more, she turned round and left the room.

They were all shocked, but the twelfth, whose good wish still remained unspoken, came forward, and as she could not undo the evil sentence, but only soften it, she said, it shall not be death, but a deep sleep of a hundred years, into which the princess shall fall.

The king, who would fain keep his dear child from the misfortune, gave orders that every spindle in the whole kingdom should be burnt. Meanwhile the gifts of the wise women were plenteously fulfilled on the young girl, for she was so beautiful, modest, good-natured, and wise, that everyone who saw her was bound to love her.

It happened that on the very day when she was fifteen years old, the king and queen were not at home, and the maiden was left in the palace quite alone. So she went round into all sorts of places, looked into rooms and bed-chambers just as she liked, and at last came to an old tower. She climbed up the narrow winding staircase, and reached a little door. A rusty key was in the lock, and when she turned it the door sprang open, and there in a little room sat an old woman with a spindle, busily spinning her flax.

"Good day, old mother," said the king"s daughter, "what are you doing there?"

"I am spinning," said the old woman, and nodded her head.

"What sort of thing is that, that rattles round so merrily," said the girl, and she took the spindle and wanted to spin too. But scarcely had she touched the spindle when the magic decree was fulfilled, and she pricked her finger with it.

And, in the very moment when she felt the prick, she fell down upon the bed that stood there, and lay in a deep sleep. And this sleep extended over the whole palace, the king and queen who had just come home, and had entered the great hall, began to go to sleep, and the whole of the court with them. The horses, too, went to sleep in the stable, the dogs in the yard, the pigeons upon the roof, the flies on the wall, even the fire that was flaming on the hearth became quiet and slept, the roast meat left off frizzling, and the cook, who was just going to pull the hair of the scullery boy, because he had forgotten something, let him go, and went to sleep. And the wind fell, and on the trees before the castle not a leaf moved again.

But round about the castle there began to grow a hedge of thorns, which every year became higher, and at last grew close up round the castle and all over it, so that there was nothing of it to be seen, not even the flag upon the roof. But the story of the beautiful sleeping Briar Rose, for so the princess was named, went about the country, so that from time to time kings' sons came and tried to get through the thorny hedge into the castle. But they found it impossible, for the thorns held fast together, as if they had hands, and the youths were caught in them, could not get loose again, and died a miserable death.

After long, long years a king's son came again to that country, and heard an old man talking about the thorn hedge, and that a castle was said to stand behind it in which a wonderfully beautiful princess, named Briar Rose, had been asleep for a hundred years, and that the king and queen and the whole court were asleep likewise. He had heard, too, from his grandfather, that many kings, sons had already come, and had tried to get through the thorny hedge, but they had remained sticking fast in it, and had died a pitiful death.

Then the youth said, "I am not afraid, I will go and see the beautiful Briar Rose." The good old man might dissuade him as he would, he did not listen to his words.

But by this time the hundred years had just passed, and the day had come when Briar Rose was to awake again. When the king's son came near to the thorn hedge, it was nothing but large and beautiful flowers, which parted from each other of their own accord, and let him pass unhurt, then they closed again behind him like a hedge. In the castle yard he saw the horses and the spotted hounds lying asleep, on the roof sat the pigeons with their heads under their wings. And when he entered the house, the flies were asleep upon the wall, the cook in the kitchen was still holding out his hand to seize the boy, and the maid was sitting by the black hen which she was going to pluck.

He went on farther, and in the great hall he saw the whole of the court lying asleep, and up by the throne lay the king and queen. Then he went on still farther, and all was so quiet that a breath could be heard, and at last he came to the tower, and opened the door into the little room where Briar Rose was sleeping.

There she lay, so beautiful that he could not turn his eyes away, and he stooped down and gave her a kiss. But as soon as he kissed her, Briar Rose opened her eyes and awoke, and looked at him quite sweetly.

Then they went down together, and the king awoke, and the queen, and the whole court, and looked at each other in great astonishment. And the horses in the courtyard stood up and shook themselves, the hounds jumped up and wagged their tails, the pigeons upon the roof pulled out their heads from under their wings, looked round, and flew into the open country, the flies on the wall crept again, the fire in the kitchen burned up and flickered and cooked the meat, the joint began to turn and sizzle again, and the cook gave the boy such a box on the ear that he screamed, and the maid finished plucking the fowl.

And then the marriage of the king's son with Briar Rose was celebrated with all splendor, and they lived contented to the end of their days.
Wasn’t this a lady of real delicacy?
</item>
        <item>unhappy - приставка *un* меняет значение на противоположное, так счастливый превращается в несчастливый. because - потому что. childless - приставка *less* становится приставкой *без*, *child* - *дитя*, *childless* - *без детей*. once - однажды. crept out - выползти. Your wish shall be fulfilled - твое желание будет исполнено, fulfilled - наполнено. year has gone by - год пройдет. shall have a daughter - будешь иметь дочь.
            came true - стало явью. so - настолько. pretty - очаровательной. contain himself for joy - сдерживать себя от радости. feast - пир. kindred and acquaintances - родственники и знакомые. well disposed - доброжелательный. to eat out of - для кушания.
with all manner of splendor - со всеми манерами великолепности. bestowed magic gifts upon the baby - одарил младенца волшебными дарами. virtue, beauty, riches, and so on - добродетельность, красота, богатсво, и так далее. that one can wish for - который любой загадал бы.

 promises - обещания. suddenly - неожиданно. wished to avenge herself - пожелала отомстить за себя. for not having been invited - за то что не была приглашена. cried - крикнула . in her fifteenth year - в свой 15-год. prick herself with a spindle - уколоть себя шпинделем. fall down dead - упасть и умереть. without saying a word more - не сказав больше слов.

shocked - шокированы. whose good wish still remained unspoken - желания которого еще не было озвучено, undo - отменить. evil sentence - злобный приговор. but only soften it - но только смягчить. not be death - не быть смертью, but a deep sleep of a hundred years - а долгим сном в сто лет.

 fain keep his dear child from the misfortune - охотно сохранить свое дорогое дите от невезения. gave orders that every spindle in the whole kingdom - отдал приказы что каждый шпиндель во всем королевстве. should be burnt - должно быть сожжено. plenteously fulfilled обильно заполнили. for she was so beautiful, modest, good-natured, and wise - что она была настолько красива, скромна, добродушна и умна. that everyone who saw her was bound to love her - что каждого кто видел ее тянуло любить ее.

It happened that on the very day when she was fifteen years old - это случилось именно в тот день когда ей стало 15 лет. maiden - девица. bed-chambers - спальни . climbed up the narrow winding staircase - поднялась по изгибающейся узкой лестнице. A rusty key was in the lock - ржавый ключ был в замке двери. sprang open - открылась отпружинив. old woman with a spindle, busily spinning her flax - сидела старая женщина с шпинделем и активно прядет свой лен.

I am spinning - я пряжу.

 that rattles round so merrily - который так весело стучит вокруг . scarcely - едва . magic decree was fulfilled - магический указ был выполнен . she pricked her finger with it - она уколола себе палец этим.

in the very moment when she felt the prick - и в тот самый момент когда она ощутила шпиндель. fell down upon the bed that stood there - упала на кровать который стоял там. lay in a deep sleep - впала долгий сон. sleep extended over the whole palace - и этот сон начал распространятся на всю территорию. who had just come home - который только что вернулись домой. the whole of the court with them - и весь особняк тоже. stable - конюшня. yard - двор. the pigeons upon the roof - голуби на крыше. flies - мухи. was flaming on the hearth became quiet and slept - огонь который горел в очаге стих и впал в сон. roast meat left off frizzling жареное мясо оставшееся без завивки. cook, who was just going to pull the hair of the scullery boy - повар который хотел дернуть за волосы судомойку. not a leaf moved again - листья не двигались.

But round about the castle - но вокруг замка. there began to grow a hedge of thorns - там начала расти живая изгородь из колючек. which every year became higher - которая становилась выше с каждым годом. and at last grew close up round the castle and all over it so that there was nothing of it to be seen - и наконец сомкнулись вокруг замка и по всему его периметру так что ничего от него не было видно . for so the princess was named - ибо так была названа принцесса. But they found it impossible - но они решили что это невозможо. *im* приставка так как и *un* меняет значение на противоположное. as if they had hands - как будто они имели руки. youths were caught in them could not get loose again and died a miserable death - дитя которые были схвачены им больше не могли выйти и умирали несчастной смертью.

wonderfully beautiful - восхитительно красивая. likewise - такде. had tried to get through the thorny hedge, but they had remained sticking fast in it, and had died a pitiful death - пытались пройти через живою изгородь но застревали и умирали жалкой смертью.

 might dissuade him as he would, he did not listen to his words - наверно уговаривал как мог, но он не слушал его слов.

day had come - день настал. which parted from each other of their own accord - которые раздвинулись друг от друга самостоятельно. let him pass unhurt - дать возможность пройти не поранившись. then they closed again behind him like a hedge - затем они закрылись за ним как изгородь. spotted hounds - пятнистые гончие . heads under their wings - головы под крыльями. seize the boy - схватить мальчика. maid - прислуга. black hen - черная курица. going to pluck - собирался схватить.

went on farther - пошел дальше. lying asleep - лежащими уснув. went on still farther - пошел еще дальше. all was so quiet that a breath could be heard - все было так тихо что вдохи были слышны.

There she lay - там она лежала. so beautiful that he could not turn his eyes away - така красивая что он не мог отвезти глаза с нее. gave her a kiss - поцеловал ее. But as soon as he kissed her - как только поцеловал ее. opened her eyes and awoke - открыла свои глаза и проснулась. looked at him quite sweetly - посмотрела на него довольно мило.

Then they went down together - они спустились вместе. and the king awoke - и король проснулся. looked at each other in great astonishment - посмотрели друг на друга в великом изумлении. courtyard - двор. stood up and shook themselves - встали и стряхнулись. hounds jumped up and wagged their tails - гончие вскочили и завиляли хвостами. looked round - осмотрели вокруг. and flew into the open country - и полетели в открытую долину. burned up and flickered and cooked the meat - загорелась вспыхнула и начала жарить мясо. cook gave the boy such a box on the ear that he screamed - кухарка дала мальчику такую затрещину, что он закричал. maid finished plucking the fowl - а служанка закончила ощипывать птицу.

marriage was celebrated with all splendor - бракосочетание было отпраздновано со всей пышностью. they lived contented to the end of their days - они жили довольные до конца своих дней.
Wasn’t this a lady of real delicacy - Разве это не была по-настоящему деликатная дама?
 </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr01q102">
        <item>1979</item>
        <item>Franko22 ANALIS</item>
        <item>text12222</item>
        <item>text analyz</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="qr01q103">
        <item>2009</item>
        <item>Franko33 ANALIS</item>
        <item>text13333333</item>
        <item>text analyz</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>